<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Case of a standing army army [sic] fairly and impartially stated in answer to the late History of standing armies in England, and other pamphlets on that subject.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35597</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C873</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3955</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13677231</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13677231</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101249</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35597)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101249)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 841:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Case of a standing army army [sic] fairly and impartially stated in answer to the late History of standing armies in England, and other pamphlets on that subject.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  History.</term>
               <term>Standing army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101249:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101249:1"/>
            <p>THE CASE Of a Standing Army ARMY Fairly and Impartially STATED. IN ANSWER To the late Hiſtory of <hi>STANDING ARMIES</hi> IN ENGLAND: And other Pamphlets writ on that Subject.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed in the Year, 1698.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101249:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101249:2"/>
            <p>THE CASE Of a Standing ARMY Freely and Impartially STATED, &amp;c.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:101249:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101249:3"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:101249:4"/>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:101249:4"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Cannot but with Grief behold, how active ſome perſons have been of late, in contriving ways to divide us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Parties and Factions. 'Tis wonderful to imagine how many Arts and Stratagems they daily make uſe of to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote their <hi>Ill Deſigns.</hi> In the War time they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually bellowing, <hi>the</hi> French <hi>wou'd be too hard for us, and ſpin out the War, till we were ruin'd by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence of it;</hi> and that, talk what we wou'd, <hi>it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible we ſhou'd ever bring our Potent Enemy to terms of Agreement, either ſafe or Honourable.</hi> This was their Trick they us'd then, to compaſs the Nation's Ruin, by diſcouraging the People from aſſiſting with their Purſes, the endeavours of his Majeſty; but God be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Wiſdom of our Parliaments, and the Love the People bore his Majeſty, caus'd us chearfully to carry on the War, to the wonder of our Enemies both at home and abroad, and Confuſion of all their dev'liſh Deſigns.</p>
            <p>And now, that we have bravely gain'd an Honourable Peace; they as Induſtriouſly wrack their wicked Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to find means to rob us of the benefits we might hope from it, and render it ineffectual, by ſetting us in Flames at home, and embroiling us into Fatal Fewds, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents; that if poſſible our Foreign Enemies may be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to them for what they were never able to do them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb facs="tcp:101249:5"/>and be forc'd for once to own, <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wits have been ſharper than <hi>French</hi> Swords. To this end they ſhift Sails, and tell us, the <hi>French</hi> are weak and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent, and unable to attempt any thing againſt us, that conſequently a <hi>Standing Army</hi> is unneceſſary, and a needleſs expence; and leaſt the People ſhou'd not regard that, they fright them with Dangers, and Chimeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Bugbears. And ſeeing theſe Men's deſigns have, in both theſe changes, evidently endeavour'd the Intereſt of our Foreign Enemies; It is not at all abſurd to imagine they have had the handling of a few <hi>Lewidores,</hi> and then we need no longer wonder at their Actions; for that Mettal carries a great weight with it; and has a way of perſwading, which their corrupted Conſciences is no wiſe able to reſiſt; Nay leaſt we ſhou'd believe they cou'd, this Author has given us two Inſtances to the contrary; in hopes perhaps of reviving here the Trade of Bribery, which to their unſpeakable Grief has been Dead ſo long.</p>
            <p>This I believe, will afford us the true cauſe of their complaining of the ſplitting and Multiplying of Places, as he calls it; for indeed if any ſober man conſiders it, he can't but think it more ſafe; and that the Truſt is likelier to be manag'd with more Integrity in the hands of many, than one; for they are as a Guard or Watch upon one another: If there be but one honeſt man in <hi>Five, Seven,</hi> or <hi>Nine,</hi> his example will oblige the reſt to be ſo too, leaſt they are found fault with; whereas there is not that obligation on a ſingle Perſon; But if there is not an honeſt man to be found in <hi>Five, Seven,</hi> or <hi>Nine;</hi> we are in a hopeleſs ſtate, and our Affairs in a deſperate Condition.</p>
            <p>If theſe Gentlemen were ſcatter'd among thoſe places, one among the <hi>Five,</hi> another among the <hi>Seven,</hi> another a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb facs="tcp:101249:5"/>the <hi>Nine,</hi> &amp;c. then I ſuppoſe, 'twou'd be full as well, as if the Commiſſions were entruſted with ſingle Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; (themſelves expected) and the places wou'd be well mannag'd to be ſure, tho' there were <hi>Ninety Nine</hi> joyn'd with them; ſo that 'tis plain their Quarrel do's not lye againſt the ſplitting of Offices; but they are angry that none of the ſplinters fell to their ſhare: They think they have as much capacity, and therefore as good pretenſions to preferment as any one. This is the ground of their Quarrels, and true reaſon of all their Complaints, and as we deal with peeviſh froward Children, the readieſt way to quiet them is to give them ſomething to <hi>Play with.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the following Pages I have endeavour'd to ſhew the <hi>Neceſſity of a Standing Force,</hi> not as they do, by what was formerly in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe; but by conſidering the Preſent Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of things, which is the only true way of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the right; for 'tis not what our Anceſtors did formerly, but what we ought to do now.</p>
            <p>Our Anceſtors acted according to the ſtate of their Affairs, and I dare affirm, if they were living now, they wou'd alter their Meaſures, to the preſent occaſions, and make no ſcruple of varying their Counſels as they ſaw neceſſity requir'd.</p>
            <p>Such a Method of acting is a ſure ſign of Wiſdom, and ſeldom fail of ſucceſs; whereas never to alter, tho' there's Neceſſity for it, ſhews Poſitiveneſs in the higheſt degree; proves incureable folly, and ever ends in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitied Miſery.</p>
            <p>Theſe Gentlemen, wiſe in their own Conceits, are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways inſtructing others; they have not patience to let the Wiſdom of the Nation act as they ſhall think fit; but by an impudent boldneſs they pretend to Model the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and regulate the Affairs of the Nation in a Club
<pb facs="tcp:101249:6"/>Room, over a heap of Sot's Weed, with as much aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance as if they were all Privy Counſellors, and are as Dogmatical and Poſitive in what they advance, as if they had chous'd the Pope of his Infallibility.</p>
            <p>They might have been ſo Civil as to have ſtay'd, to ſee what His Majeſty's thoughts were, and what the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament will do in the buſineſs; ſince all good Men are aſſur'd, that His Majeſty will never intend, nor the Parliament ever conſent, to any thing, but what will be evidently for the <hi>Glory, Honour,</hi> and <hi>Safety</hi> of theſe Nations.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101249:6"/>
            <head>THE CASE Of a Standing ARMY Freely and Impartially STATED, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>'TIS not at all ſtrange to ſee the beſt things Evil ſpoken of. The Wiſeſt Counſels and moſt Regular Conduct have often been ſeverely Cenſur'd even by thoſe who have largely ſhar'd their good Effects. There have been ſome in all Ages, who have had ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant and unhappy mixture of Ill-nature in their Conſtitutions, that they have taken a pleaſure to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101249:7"/>be always out of Humour, ever complaining and murmuring, never pleas'd with either good or bad Fortune; and ſince the whole delight of ſuch wretches conſiſts in a conſtant exerciſe of their Spleen, they take care never to want this dev'liſh diverſion, by continually employing themſelves in finding faults in others; not putting themſelves to the trouble of diſtinguiſhing between <hi>Good,</hi> and <hi>Ill,</hi> unleſs it be to beſtow their bittereſt Reproaches where they find the greateſt Excellencies, becauſe moſt directly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to their own Imperfections.</p>
            <p>That this is the caſe of moſt of our <hi>Malecontents</hi> I believe we may be pretty ſure; for it can eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſhewn, that the very <hi>ſame</hi> Perſons have been <hi>noted Grumbletonians</hi> in the Luxurious and Effemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the II. the Arbitrary and Tyrannical Reign of the late King <hi>James,</hi> and ſtill keep up their ſnarling Humours even in the Mild and Eaſie one of his preſent Majeſty King <hi>William:</hi> So that 'tis plain the fault lies only in their own <hi>corrupted Blood</hi> and <hi>vicious Tempers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That ſuch People ſhou'd have any regard, or that any one ſhou'd be drawn in to mind or value, much leſs to cry up, their wicked Inſinuations and miſcheivous Complaints, which have no other ſource than the too great abundance of their Spleen, and their own ſettled ill diſpoſitions, which no Art can correct or cure, is a very ſurprizing and ſad Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and ought to be dreaded by every good perſon; for in the end the Conſequences may prove very fatal and prejudicial.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:101249:7"/>
            <p>Amongſt theſe ſort of Men none have made a greater Noiſe or ſeem'd to have more plauſible pretences, than thoſe Perſons who have employ'd their Pens in terrifying the People with the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of a Standing Army. <hi>Liberty</hi> is their Cry, a Glorious Topick indeed when it is not abus'd; but it has ever been made the Stalking-Horſe to all De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and dreſs'd up in as various ſhapes as the Witt and Cunning of Deſigning Perſons found ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and convenient to their Ends and Purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; 'tis an Argument very ſpecious and plauſible, never failing to dazle the Eyes of the Unthinking Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, who run away with the word, and conſider no farther than the bare out ſide of things.</p>
            <p>Whether or no there lies any ill Deſigns, at the bottom of the preſent clamour againſt a Standing Army, I know not; but I am afraid of what might follow if theſe Gentlemens Notions were embrac'd, and their deſires ſatisfyed; I cannot but think we ſhou'd be in very ill Circumſtances if we were left Unguarded, and without Forces ſufficient to ſecure us from the Inſults of our Enemies; but I hope their ill counſels will never prevail to reduce us to ſo lamentable a condition, as to be more beholden to the Generoſity or Imprudence of an Enemy, than to our own Strength and Wiſdom.</p>
            <p>Nay I dare engage, that theſe ſame Gentlemen, who are now ſo very hot for the Disbanding the Army, ſhou'd the Army be Disbanded, wou'd be ſo far from being better ſatisfied, or cur'd of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101249:8"/>ſpleenetick Humours they are overrun with, that they wou'd then make the <hi>Want</hi> of an Army the Grounds and Occaſions of new Complaints; they wou'd then with open Mouths, and a full Cry, and with ſomething more reaſon on their ſide, roar out, that we were neither ſafe nor ſecure, but left naked and defenceleſs to a Potent and Inveterate Enemy, who might, (if he pleas'd) make an eaſie Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of us, and quickly be Maſter both of our Lives and Eſtates; This wou'd then be the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry, and we ſhou'd be Impos'd on with the continual AIarms of an Invaſion from abroad, by the very <hi>ſame</hi> Perſons, who now endeavour to frighten us with the Loſs of our Freedom and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties by an Army at home; the grumbling Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor wou'd ſtill find ſomething to feed on, and preſerve it ſelf alive in ſpite of either Cure or Poiſon.</p>
            <p>But to begin with our Author of the <hi>Hiſtory of Standing Armies in</hi> England; Page firſt he ſays, <hi>If any Man doubts whether a ſtanding Army is Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, Popery, Mahometiſm, Paganiſm, Atheiſm, or any thing which they pleaſe.</hi> How <hi>Sir,</hi> A <hi>Standing Army</hi> to be ſo many ſeveral things or what you pleaſe, this is ſtrange indeed, and if this is all, we need not fear; for to be every thing, or what you pleaſe, is to be nothing at all, I admire this Gentleman ſhou'd ſtumble on ſo odd a beginning; but to go on, <hi>let him read firſt, the ſtory of</hi> Matho <hi>and</hi> Spendius <hi>at</hi> Carthage; <hi>Secondly, the Hiſtories of</hi> Strada <hi>and</hi> Bentivoglio: <hi>where he will find what work Nine Thouſand</hi> Spaniards <hi>made in the 17 Provinces, tho'
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101249:8"/>the Country was full of fortified Towns, poſſeſs'd by the Low-Country Lords, and they had aſſiſtance from</hi> Germany, England <hi>and</hi> France. I think this one Paragraph is a direct Confutation of the whole Book; for if Nine Thouſand <hi>Spaniards</hi> well Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plin'd, made ſuch havock in the 17 Provinces, tho' the Country was full of fortified Towns, and in the Poſſeſſion of the Low-Country Lords, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted too by <hi>Germany, England</hi> and <hi>France;</hi> I think we, (who can't boaſt of many ſtrong fortified Towns, nor can't reaſonably expect any quick Aſſiſtance from Abroad,) ſhou'd think of keeping up a Force able and ſufficient to protect us in caſe of Neceſſity, and not of leaving our ſelves Open and Unguarded; this is ſo very obvious to the meaneſt degree of Senſe, that I wonder how theſe Gentlemen or any one elſe can have a thought to the contrary.</p>
            <p>But he goes on confuting his own Notions; for he confeſſes <hi>that we have always had an Eſtabliſh'd Force among us,</hi> if ſo, then I think the diſpute may be brought into a narrow Compaſs; for the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will not be, <hi>if a Standing Force here is Legal;</hi> for that's granted, but the queſtion will be, <hi>what Forces are Neceſſary to be kept in Pay at this time;</hi> which may be immediately reſolv'd, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering what an Army is rais'd and kept in Pay for; and it is either to <hi>Invade</hi> and <hi>Offend</hi> our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, or to be a <hi>Security</hi> and <hi>Defence</hi> to our ſelves, when we have reaſon to fear an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noyance or Invaſion from Abroad; and I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe all <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> will ſee the occaſion of a <hi>Standing Force,</hi> and a pretty large one too; for if
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101249:9"/>we have not an <hi>Army ſufficient for our Security and Preſervation, we had as good have none;</hi> ſo that all the pains this Gentleman has been at in computing the Forces now in Pay, on purpoſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtill Fears and Jealouſies in the hearts of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty's good Subjects, is to no manner of purpoſe, unleſs it be to give us the greater reaſon to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in our Security, and to thank God that we are ſo well provided for our Defence. 'Tis true indeed we have juſt had a Peace; which gives theſe Gentlemen occaſion to ſay, that we have nothing to fear, and conſequently no Uſe for an Army, but if we conſider how apt a certain Prince is to diſturb and Invade his Neighbours, and how able he is at this time to do it; how often alſo he has found pretences to break the moſt Solemn Leagues, we ſhou'd quickly be convinc'd of the contrary, and find very good Grounds to fear an attempt upon us if we are not able to prevent it. In Page 3 he highly extolls the Merits of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and deſervedly too, he tells us, <hi>She aſſiſted the Dutch,</hi> whereby She trained up her Subjects in the Art of War, <hi>That She wou'd never permit them nor</hi> France <hi>to build any great Ships; kept the Keys of the</hi> Maes <hi>and</hi> Scheld <hi>in her own hands; and died with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>control'd Dominion of the Seas, and Arbitreſs of Chriſtendom; all this She did with a Revenue not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding</hi> 300000 <hi>l.</hi> per Annum, <hi>and had but inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Taxes from her People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To diſpute with theſe Men, we muſt ſet things in a right Light. 'Tis plain, they built upon falſe ſuppoſitions, which few People obſerve, being dazled
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101249:9"/>with the plauſibleneſs of their Arguments, and blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with their pretended concern for their Country; but to argue truly upon the matter, and to ſtate the Caſe aright, we muſt conſider the Alterations, and Revolutions, that have happen'd in <hi>Europe,</hi> within theſe hundred Years. <hi>France</hi> is now arriv'd to a vaſt Height, 'tis now no more that <hi>France</hi> which we could Invade and almoſt Conquer at our plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. We may indeed forbid them building great Ships, but I fancy they wou'd hardly mind us. Ships they have to compoſe a ſtrong and mighty Fleet, with Seamen able and experienc'd to Man them, great Armies at Land in conſtant Pay; this is a State far differing from what they were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly; therefore we go a wrong way to work, when we <hi>ſuppoſe them in the ſame condition they were in a hundred Years ago,</hi> and build <hi>Maxims for preſent uſe on thoſe ſuppoſitions;</hi> for 'tis evident they are encreas'd to an incredible pitch in extent of their Country, Riches, and multitudes of the Inhabitants; that this is no groundleſs ſuppoſition, is very clear, by their being able to cope with a Confederacy of the moſt Potent Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> for ten Years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: As the Author of the account of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> ſays in his Preface, <hi>we have lately bought the experience of this truth too dear not to be now ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of it. 'Tis not very long ago ſince nothing was-more generally believ'd (even by Men of the beſt Senſe) than that the Power of</hi> England <hi>was ſo unqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly eſtabliſh'd at Sea, that no Force cou'd poſſibly ſhake it; that the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Valour and Manner of Fighting was ſo far beyond all others, that nothing was more deſirable than a War with</hi> France. <hi>Shou'd any
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101249:10"/>one have been ſo regardleſs of his reputation at that time to have repreſented the</hi> French <hi>an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>match for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Forces of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; <hi>or have ſaid, that we ſhou'd live to ſee our ſelves inſulted on our own Coaſts, and our Trade endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger'd by them, that we ſhou'd be in apprehenſions of an Invaſion and a</hi> French <hi>Conqueſt, ſuch a ventureſome Man muſt hav e expected to have paſs'd for a very Traveller, or at beſt, for an illnatur'd and unthink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Perſon, who little conſider'd what the reſiſtleſs Force of an</hi> Engliſh <hi>Arm was; but our late Expertence has reclaim'd us from theſe Miſtakes: Our Fathers and Grand Fathers told us indeed theſe things,</hi> when they were true, <hi>when our Yeomanry and Commonalty were every day Exercis'd in drawing</hi> the Long Bow, <hi>and handling</hi> the Brown Bill, <hi>with other Weapons</hi> then in uſe, <hi>wherein we excell'd all the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſet this ſtill in a clearer Light, 'twill not be amiſs if we conſider the State of <hi>England</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of what it was formerly; and I believe we may, without much thought, affirm that our Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy was at its higheſt pitch in the Reign of our glorious Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the remiſsneſs and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſsneſs of ſome of the late Reigns have ſoften'd our Spirits, and brought a Luxury unknown to our Fore-Fathers in vogue among us, whereby we are degenerated from that old hardineſs and Fortitude, our Anceſtors were ſo famous for. This being the true State of the Caſe without partiality on either ſide; theſe Gentlemens Notions will naturally fall to peices; and I hope that true Engliſhmen will no longer ſuffer themſelves to be impos'd on by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101249:10"/>a ſingle of Words, that have only an empty ſound to recommend them; 'tis time I think to look a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout us, and conſider ſeriouſly on the matter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we part with thoſe Forces that have ſo bravely fought for us Abroad, and are ſtill ſo willing and able to defend us at Home: But before I part with this Gentleman on this head, I can't but take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the ſly Inſinuation he makes of Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth's</hi> doing all thoſe great things with only 300000 <hi>l. per Annum,</hi> and ſome inconſiderable Taxes beſides; his deſign is that Peple ſhou'd immediately make reflections on the Taxes that have been rais'd to Maintain this War; but if this Gentleman had that Ingenuity he pretends to, he wou'd hinder ſuch Reflections, by letting us know that ſuch a Summ was more than 3 times as much in our Days, and that by her Privateers She took ſeveral Millions from the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> beſides the Cuſtoms and Intereſt were paid her by the <hi>Dutch,</hi> with theſe She did all thoſe great things: that She had but an Army between 1400 and 2000 Men in time of Peace is evidently falſe; for there were a greater Number than that requiſite to the Garriſoning of the Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionary Towns in her hands in <hi>Flanders;</hi> but I think 'tis needleſs to follow him in his Hiſtorical Account or things, for they are very little, to his purpoſe, or indeed to any purpoſe at all.</p>
            <p>In Page 19 he tells us, <hi>That his preſent Majeſty was invited over, and landed at</hi> Torbay, <hi>publiſhing a Declaration, which ſet forth all the Oppreſſions of the late Reign,</hi> (but the keeping up a Standing Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my) <hi>declar'd for a free Parliament, in which things
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101249:11"/>were to be ſo ſettled, that there ſhou'd be no danger of falling again into Slavery; and promis'd to ſend back all his foreign Forces as ſoon as this was done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sure theſe Gentlemen imagine they may ſay any thing; they are great Inſtances of the Mildneſs of the preſent Government, when they are not brought to an Account, for taking ſuch Liberties both in their Speech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and Writings, to Inſinuate whatever they think may be prejudicial to thoſe above them; for to tell us that a <hi>Standing Army</hi> is certain Slavery, and to Inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate that his preſent Majeſty intended from the very firſt to maintain a <hi>Standing Army,</hi> is as plain as they can ſpeak, to aſperſe His Majeſty with what they daily experience to be falſe: ſuch Liberties are too bold, and that they are not call'd to Account for them, is plain demonſtration of the Idleneſs and Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their Fears.</p>
            <p>Here again he lays t he blame of <hi>Ireland</hi>'s not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing timely ſuccour'd on the Government, when we all know how earneſt His Majeſty was for the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of thoſe diſtreſſed People; tho' he tell us, that <hi>Ireland</hi> was neglected to be relieved, for a pretence for the raiſing a greater Army; I wou'd have theſe Gentlemen take care how they provoke Mercy.</p>
            <p>In Page 21, he tells us, <hi>the King acquainted the Parliament the 8th of</hi> March, <hi>when ſpeaking of the deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Condition of</hi> Ireland, <hi>that he thought it not adviſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to undertake the reducing of it, with leſs than</hi> 20000 <hi>Horſe and Foot. This was a better Pill to the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, who thought they might have managed their
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101249:11"/>ſhare of the War with</hi> France <hi>by a Fleet at Sea, but there was no Remedy, a greater Army muſt be rais'd, or</hi> Ireland <hi>loſt.</hi> This Gentleman writes fiaſt I ſuppoſe, and ſeldom minds his Senſe. Did the Parliament think of Conquering <hi>Ireland</hi> by a Fleet? He wou'd have had them landed their Seamen, and left their Ships a prey to the <hi>French.</hi> We'll forgive him one blunder however, if he'll take care what he writes hereafter: but I admire how this Gentleman makes the Conqueſt of <hi>Ireland</hi> and a War with <hi>France</hi> the ſame thing; for I take them to be diſtinct: <hi>Ireland</hi> is our own Country, and when we fought for that, we fought for what was immediate ely our own, we were not at War with <hi>France,</hi> or any Foreign Prince, we were reducing a People, who were in actual Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> but we'll not quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel about Terms; tho' by the way, the miſeries and hardſhips our Fellow Subjects of <hi>Ireland</hi> felt, ſhou'd make us terribly afraid of giving any Neighbouring Prince the leaſt hopes of ſucceeding in any Attempt upon us; for 'tis an undeniable Maxim, <hi>that opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity makes the Thief,</hi> and by <hi>Disbanding</hi> our Troops, we may poſſibly give ſome grounds for hopes of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to a Prince naturally Aſpiring and Ambitious, and very apt to fancy himſelf capable of doing more than he is able; but to return, I wou'd ask this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman how he came to be ſo ſure <hi>that the Parliament thought to have managed their ſhare of this War by a Fleet at Sea,</hi> which he ſo poſſitively aſſerts. We are all ſure that the Parliaments of <hi>England</hi> were of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mind in former Days, or they wou'd never have contributed ſo largely and liberally towards an Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>France</hi> as they often did, Nay, in all our
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101249:12"/>Hiſtories, I never found they ever parted with their Money more heartily, than when it was for a War with that Country, and yet they never ſo much as dream't of their carrying on a War, only by a Fleet at Sea, but quite the contrary; for we all of us know, that our Kings very frequently Tranſported great Armies over into <hi>Flanders, Normandy,</hi> or ſome part of <hi>France,</hi> thinking it more adviſeable to Seat the War in an Enemies Country rather than their own. To give ſome Inſtances,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror enter'd <hi>France</hi> with a great Army. <hi>William Rufus</hi> Invaded <hi>Normandy,</hi> ſo did <hi>Henry</hi> the V. and <hi>Richard</hi> the I. <hi>Henry</hi> the III. twice Tranſported great Armies over to <hi>France. Edward</hi> the I. twice Invaded <hi>France.</hi> There were no leſs than five ſeveral Armies Tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted over to <hi>France</hi> in the Reign of <hi>Edward</hi> the II. <hi>Henry</hi> the V. had continually an Army in <hi>France.</hi> Many more Inſtances might, be given of the like nature, but theſe are enough to let us ſee, that in former times our Parliaments thought it no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution to their Wiſdom to carry on their Warrs in Foreign Parts by Land-Forces; tho' in thoſe Days they were confeſſedly ſtronger at Sea than any of their Neighbours; and amongſt all our Princes we find none more belov'd, and extoll'd, than thoſe Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Monarchs, who Tranſported and Headed their <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Armies in Foreign Parts. Beſides, whoever do's but conſider how liberally and largely our late Parliaments have contributed towards the Expence of a ten Years War, and what a happy Agreement and Union there has been all along betwixt the King and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101249:12"/>them, I ſay, whoever conſiders this, can by no means believe he ſpeakes truth, when he tells us, <hi>that the Parliament thought they might have manag'd their ſhare of the War with</hi> France <hi>by a Fleet at Sea, and that they thought the raiſing a Land Force a bitter Pill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I think this Gentleman ſhould be requir'd to give a more publick account of this Aſſertion. To make us believe the King out-witted the Parliament, and that the Parliament themſelves acted diſagreeably to their own opinions, this is a New contrivance, and may in time produce very evil Conſequences. But I hope Men of Senſe will take care how they are ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jol'd by ſuch horrid Inſinuations.</p>
            <p>Well, now he comes to his dear beloved Militia, and tells us what wonders were done in <hi>Ireland</hi> by the <hi>Iniskilling-Men,</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Londonderry;</hi> but pray let us ſtop a little to conſider the matter, and not ſuffer this Phamphleteer to run away with Noiſe and Nonſenſe. The <hi>Iniskilling Men</hi> were People made deſperate by the Ruins of their Eſtates and Fortunes, almoſt weary of their Lives by the Cruelties and Hardſhips they ſuffer'd from the <hi>Iriſh Papiſts,</hi> having the cries of their Wives and Children, (labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring under the greateſt Miſeries) ever in their Ears, and the deplorable condition of their <hi>Native Country</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their Eyes; beſide they were not a <hi>Militia,</hi> as our Author falſely boaſts, but were for the moſt part Gentlemen and others that ſled from the Barbarities of the <hi>Iriſh Papiſts</hi> from all parts of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd in a Body for their ſecurity at <hi>Iniskilling,</hi> and great Numbers of them Officers and private Soldiers
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101249:13"/>of the Army, whom <hi>Tryconnel</hi> had Disbanded becauſe Proteſtants, Men that had been in Pay and Diſcipline a great part of the Reign of King <hi>Chales</hi> the II. So that 'tis a miſtake to ſay they were a <hi>Militia;</hi> far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, if it be conſider'd whom they fought with, there's none will wonder at what they did, they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred poor ſenſeleſs wretches that knew not their Right hands from their Left; and always look be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them when they draw their Swords. And if theſe are the Wonders they boaſt of, they had as good be ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, and ſay nothing of the matter.</p>
            <p>In the next Page he ſays, <hi>at laſt by our great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and Fleets, and the conſtant Expence of maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, we were too hard for the OEconomy, Skill, and Policy of</hi> France, <hi>and notwithſtanding all our difficulties, brought them to terms both Safe and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable.</hi> Did we ſo <hi>Sir.</hi> then I think we have very little reaſon to complain, and if our <hi>Fleet and Armies</hi> procur'd us this Peace, They only can preſerve it; by parting with <hi>either</hi> we make it precarious, and to depend meerly on the <hi>Generoſity</hi> of an Enemy, who is not us'd to be firmer to his Word than his Intereſt; ſeveral true ſenſible <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> are of the opinion, that the longer we maintain a <hi>Standing Armed Force,</hi> we ſhall be the longer from having Occaſion to make uſe of them; but that on the contrary, the ſooner we <hi>Disband</hi> them, the ſooner we ſhall be put to the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and charge of raiſing New; For 'tis certainly true, that that Nation which is moſt <hi>able</hi> to wage War, will be the unlikelieſt to be put to the trouble of it.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:101249:13"/>
            <p>But here he ſays, <hi>I ſhall omit giving any account of the Conduct of our Fleet during this War, how few Advantages we reap'd by it, and how many occaſions was loſt of Deſtroying the</hi> French; <hi>only thus much I will Obſerve, that tho' a great part of it may be attributed to the Negligence, Ignorance, or Treachery of Inferior Officers, yet it cou'd not univerſally happen</hi> (the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman is poſitive in what he ſays) <hi>and unpuniſh'd too, notwithſtanding the Clamours of the Merchants, and repeated complaints in Parliament, unleſs the Cauſe had laid deeper.</hi> Now this Gentleman ſhou'd take care to be well inform'd, before he ſo poſſitively Aſſerts things of this Nature; he may be call'd on to give an Account of his knowledge in the Affairs he pretends to be ſo well acquainted with, and it may go very hard with him if he can't prove what he Affirms, and produce Grounds for his malicious Inſinuations; but if he is inform'd of the Nature of Affairs, and ſo well knows the miscarriages that have befell us, where the Source and Original of them lay, their ſecret Springs and Movements; he ought, eſpecially ſince he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to be ſuch a <hi>Patriot,</hi> to have pointed out the Perſons, diſcover'd the Authors, and openly accus'd them to the World; for <hi>God</hi> be thanked, none need be ſilent now in a juſt Cauſe, none need be afraid or backward to reveal the Truth; we are unacquainted with <hi>Threats</hi> and <hi>Cloſettings</hi> ſo frequent in the <hi>late Reigns,</hi> and are neither Brib'd nor terrified out of the Truth; if they are only his own private Suggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Chimera's rais'd and fomented by his own ill Humors, he ought to have forbore them, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at this time of Day, when they may embroil the King and Parliament into Heats and Jealouſies of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101249:14"/>each other, which might create greater hardſhips to the Nation, than the whole ten Years War, and might prove more fatal in the end.</p>
            <p>However, to ſatisfie theſe murmuring Gentlemen in this point, we may give very good reaſons that our Affairs at Sea were not manag'd to more advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and alſo that they are not capable of being bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter manag'd without our having a <hi>Land Force</hi> at home; for the <hi>French King</hi> found his Account lay in <hi>Pyrating</hi> on our Merchants, where ſomething was to be had, rather than in Fighting our Fleets, where, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Uncertainty of Victory, nothing but dry Blows were to be gain'd; whereas, by taking our Trading Veſſels, he not only impoveriſh'd us, but at the ſame time enrich'd himſelf, which was a double advantage; and to hinder this Misfortune there was no way but one, that was the dividing our Fleet, as he did his, into ſeveral ſmall Squadrons, and ſend them Cruiſing, and Coaſting about in all places where our Merchants had any buſineſs; but then the Remedy wou'd have been worſe than the Diſeaſe; for we ſhou'd have left ourſelves <hi>Open</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> at a time when our King was out of the Nation, and all our Forces in <hi>Flanders;</hi> and I believe the <hi>French</hi> wou'd ſcarce have let ſlip'd the opportunity of Invading us, and hardly fail'd of making their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of ſuch an Over-ſight. This I think is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to convince theſe <hi>Purblind Politicians</hi> of the <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of a <hi>Standing Army;</hi> for if a War ſhou'd break out again, having a <hi>Land Force</hi> to ſecure us, our Fleet may divide themſelves, and either block our Enemies in their own Ports, or attend and Convoy
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101249:14"/>our Merchants in all places of Danger, ſo hinder our Enemies from Enriching themſelves by our Loſſes; Whereas, if we are without a <hi>Land Force</hi> ſufficient to Protect us, our <hi>Naval Forces</hi> cou'd take little care of our Merchants (whereby they wou'd every where, become an eaſie Prey to the Enemies Privateers) for they muſt keep together in a Body at home, to be able to ſecure us from Invaſions, leaſt our Enemies ſhou'd come upon us; ſo while we were Protect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Trade, we might loſe the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Now he comes to his Computations, which as I ſaid, ſignifie nothing to the purpoſe, unleſs it be to make us rejoyce that we are in ſo good a Condition to reſiſt our <hi>Enemies Abroad,</hi> for I know of none we have at home; if he knows of any, let him ſpeak out, which I ſuppoſe is more than he is willing to do: 'Tis generally obſerv'd of ſuch as make the greateſt Noiſe and Stir, that they are always the readieſt to pull in their Horns, and cry they know nothing of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Beſides when he was computing, 'twou'd have been but a little more trouble to have inform'd us the Number of the <hi>French Forces,</hi> and what Troops the <hi>Dutch</hi> and other Nations have in Pay, this wou'd have been very convenient, we might have known the <hi>Strength</hi> of our <hi>Neighbours</hi> as well as our ſelves, and then perhaps thought it might be prudent to keep it up in ſome tolerable degree of equality with theirs; this I am perſuaded would be the natural reſult of our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting on their great Strength.</p>
            <p>If indeed this Gentleman, or any of his Adherents, cou'd actually engage our <hi>Neighbours</hi> to <hi>Disband their Forces,</hi> we ſhou'd no longer diſpute this point with him,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101249:15"/>but I ſuppoſe this is more than he will promiſe; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſince all around us are in Arms, and entertain <hi>vaſt Numbers of Armed Troops</hi> in conſtant Pay, 'twou'd be a fatal blot in our Politicks to part with ours; for, <hi>ſince the Practice is grown ſo general, No King or Prince, tho' endowed with never ſo peaceable a Spirit, and never ſo deſirous of being at eaſe, dares lead the Dance and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arm, for fear of his Armed Neighbours, whoſe Neceſſities or Ambition make them wait only for an opportunity to fall upon him that is worſt provided to make reſiſtance.</hi> So that while our <hi>Neighbours</hi> keep up their <hi>Standing Forces,</hi> 'tis evident we muſt do ſo, unleſs we will ſubmit our ſelves to be Inſulted by them.</p>
            <p>Farther, when this Gentleman tells us the greatneſs of our <hi>Standing Forces</hi> now, and that in former Days they were very inconſiderable, he only lets us know juſt as much as will ſerve his own turn and no more, for there's a vaſt alteration crept into the very Conſtitution of our Government within theſe hundred and fifty Years; formerly the Nobility and Gentry held their Poſſeſſions and Lands from the Crown by <hi>Knight's Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</hi> and ſo were always bound to attend on their Kings in his Wars with certain Numbers of Armed Men, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Tenure and Extent of their ſeveral Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips or Lands, and they had their <hi>Villains or Vaſſals,</hi> who, by a like Tenure from them, were oblig'd to wait on their reſpective Lords or Landlords, when requir'd for the Service of their King and Country, and that they might not be Undiſciplin'd when they were call'd for, every Pariſh was to take care that all Boys ſhou'd at ſet times Exerciſe the Arms then in Uſe, as Shooting in Bows, handling the Battle Ax, and ſuch like; ſo that by this Method there was no occaſion for any great
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101249:15"/>
               <hi>Standing Force,</hi> for the People were Soldiers themſelves, and might be rais'd on any ſudden Occaſion, by the Kings giving Notice to the Nobility and Gentry of his want of their Service, and by their immediate Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moning their <hi>Vaſſals</hi> for the Attendance they were bound to pay. 'Twill be immediately reply'd why may it not be ſo now, by this means we might rid our ſelves of the fears of a <hi>Standing Army,</hi> and yet be able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend our ſelves, or Annoy our Enemy. To this I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, I ſhou'd be very glad if ſome ſuch Method cou'd be taken now, and a <hi>Militia</hi> formed capable of mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging their ſhare of War, and ſupporting our Credit and Reputation Abroad in the World, without our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put to the Uneaſineſs and Expence of a <hi>Standing Force,</hi> for I am not ſo raſh as to affirm a <hi>Standing Army</hi> to be at all a <hi>Benefit</hi> or <hi>Advantage</hi> to the Nation, if it might be diſpens'd with on good Terms, no, rather quite the contrary, I think the only Reaſon, that can be giving for the keeping a <hi>Standing Force</hi> in Pay, is <hi>Neceſſity:</hi> But I hardly think a <hi>Mititia</hi> can be form'd to ſerve our occaſions now. For,</p>
            <p>Firſt, by the cunning and contrivance of Humane reach and Invention, and the charge of Times and Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, War now is become a Trade, it conſiſts not ſo much in ſtrength of Body, or a real Courage, as in Slight and Witt; to be able to fortifie Camps and Towns, to draw your Enemy into Ambuſcades, or drill him along into diſadvantageous Places, to be able to draw him to Battle, or ſecure your ſelf from being forc'd to one, theſe are now the beſt Martial Qualifications, and theſe are things muſt be learnt by <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> none can be perfect in them but by <hi>Experience,</hi> there muſt be an <hi>Apprenticeſhip</hi> ſerv'd for the learning them.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101249:16"/>This I think is ſufficient, to make us believe that a <hi>Militia</hi> can very hardly be ſo regulated, as to prove uſeful at this time of Day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> Suppoſing a <hi>Militia</hi> might be brought to good Diſcipline and Order, yet twou'd be a very great while before ſuch a thing cou'd be done, and wou'd theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate Gentlemen have us leave our ſelves <hi>Naked</hi> and <hi>Open</hi> all the time, this wou'd be an Imprudence that our Enemies perhaps wou'd be glad to find us guilty of, ſince I believe they only wou'd be the gainers by it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly,</hi> Tho' our <hi>Militia</hi> was ſerviceable, yet we ſhou'd find very few of them forward to go over to any Foreign Parts, where it might be convenient and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for us to employ our Forces, for they wou'd be Men that were ſettled and fixt by Wives and Families at home, whereas our <hi>Standing Forces</hi> (the Private Soldiers) are moſt of them Men that have no fixt Habitations are not ty'd at home by Wives and Families, but taken either young before they had ſettled themſelves, or moſtly from among thoſe that were Vagabonds, and Wanderers, that had no buſineſs, and were rather a Burthen than Benefit to their Country, but by being put into the Army are now become uſeful and benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to it; whereas if they are Disbanded, what can be expected from ſuch people, who are not fixt at home by the tye of Families or Intereſt, but to go abroad, atd enter into any Service that will be ſo kind as to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them; and who can blame them, ſince they know no other way of Livelihood; the Conſequence of which thing alone might fright us from what theſe Gentlemen wou'd have us immediately do, and make us very cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious how we part from that Force, which have done
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101249:16"/>us ſo much good even when they were but learning their Trade, which at our Coſt and Expences they have learnt ſo well as to be Maſters of; but by Disbanding them, and turning them abroad, we give our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours the opportunity of reaping the Profit and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</p>
            <p>But this Gentleman tells us <hi>we need not ſend Forces into Foreign Parts, we need only have a ſtrong Fleet at Sea, and that wou'd be ſecurity enough:</hi> But I think the Practice of all our Kings and Parliaments, as I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready Inſtanc'd, may be enough to confute one part of this Aſſertion; for I take it, our Fore Fathers were as wiſe and knowing in what concern'd their Intereſt, as any of us now can pretend to; and if we loak back into former Stories we ſhall find enough to convince us of the folly of truſting too much to the other part; by ſeeing what has happen'd, we ſhall quickly find that a Fleet will not ſecure us from Invaſions. To give ſome Inſtances to theſe Poſitive Gentlemen, How often did the <hi>Danes</hi> land great Numbers of Armed Forces, in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt every part of this Iſland? continually alarming the poor People, ruining and making horrible devaſtations wherever they came; exerciſing all manner of Barbara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties on the poor unprovided <hi>Engliſh,</hi> putting whole Towns, Men, Women and Children to the Sword; till at laſt they Lorded it over the whole Iſland; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps there are a People in the World, wou'd not be much civiller on an occaſion, which God forbid they ſhou'd ever have; and which while we have a good Army, we need not fear; but to give ſome more Inſtances. <hi>William</hi> the Conqueror landed with an Army here, ſo did his Son <hi>Robert,</hi> Duke of <hi>Normandy,</hi> in the Reign of <hi>William Rufus,</hi> and in the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> the Firſt. The
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101249:17"/>Empreſs <hi>Maud</hi> landed an Army in the Reign of King <hi>Stephen,</hi> ſo did <hi>Henry</hi> II. The <hi>French</hi> Invaded the Land in the Reign of <hi>Henry</hi> III. Queen <hi>Iſabel</hi> landed with an Army at <hi>Orwel,</hi> in <hi>Suſſex,</hi> in the Reign of <hi>Edward</hi> the Second. <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh landed with an Army, tho' <hi>Richard</hi> the Third took all poſſible care to hinder him. And whenever there have been heats and diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents in this Kingdom, the <hi>French</hi> have ever aſſiſted one or another party to keep up the Contention; tho' our Princes by their Fleets have always endeavour'd to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it. Theſe are enough to convince every lover of his Country, of the falſity of theſe Gentlemen's, ſaying that a Fleet only is able to protect us.</p>
            <p>Perhaps they will object againſt what has been ſaid, and ſay, That in thoſe days we were weak at Sea, but that now we are grown much ſtronger. So is our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours too, as we very well know by experience; I ſcarce think any of theſe angry Gentlemen will venture to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that we are at this time, the moſt potent at Sea, or that none of our Neighbours dare to look us in the face on that Element; whereas in former days, tho' we were but mean at Sea, in compariſon of what we are now; yet our Neighbours were much meaner, we were formerly confeſſedly the moſt powerful in Shipping, and enjoyed an abſolute and uncontroul'd dominion on the Seas; and if in thoſe days, when we bore ſo great a ſway on the Ocean, and all the Nations around us ſo little, a Fleet cou'd not hinder Armies from landing in <hi>England;</hi> I can't think how it ſhou'd do it now, when our Neighbours are as ſtrong in Shipping, and as Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful at Sea as our Selves. This I think is a plain caſe, an Argument ſo clear, that I wonder how any ſenſible per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons can overlook it. And if we may be Invaded, tho'
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101249:17"/>we have a good Fleet, as 'tis plain we may, we ſhou'd be careful how we parted with a Land Force; which wou'd then be our only ſafety, and can be no Injury at all to us, as long as his Majeſty is ſo clearly in the Intereſt of his People.</p>
            <p>All this great Clamour and Noiſe againſt a <hi>Standing Army,</hi> can have no other meaning than this, That they dare not truſt his Majeſty, or rely on his Integrity; theſe are hard things, and a very ungrateful way of dealing with a Prince, who has all his Life-time hazarded his Perſon for the relief and ſuccour of the Diſtreſſed; who cou'd never be wrought upon, either by bribes or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naces, to be unjuſt to his word, even in the ſmalleſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle; a Prince whoſe ſingle Reputation cauſed a ſtrict band and Union amongſt Princes of the moſt diſagreeing Intereſts, Humours, and Religions. That this Prince ſhou'd be miſtruſted by a People of the <hi>ſame Religion,</hi> is a thing wonderful and ſurprizing; and will hardly be credited in after Ages, eſpecially when they ſhall know that he <hi>reſcue'd theſe ſame People from the Jaws of Slavery and Popery;</hi> and ſav'd them juſt ſinking into the Pit of Deſtruction; but this is more than theſe Gentlemen dare openly own; therefore they complain againſt the <hi>Court,</hi> and the <hi>Government;</hi> concealing their baſe Reflections and ill-manner'd Inſinuations, under double and ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guous meanings; but the skreen is too thin and tranſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; 'tis eaſily ſeen through, and their throughts as readily apprehended as if they had writ them at length.</p>
            <p>But to go on with this Gentleman, and come to his <hi>Criſis,</hi> Page 42, where he ſays, <hi>ſeveral Accidents con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur to make the Disbanding of an Army practicable which may not happen again.</hi> To be even with him, and give
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101249:18"/>him a <hi>Rowland</hi> for his <hi>Oliver;</hi> ſeveral Accidents concur to oblige us to keep up a <hi>Standing Army</hi> here, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver did happen, nor never may again: There's a King beyond Sea, who maintains pretenſions to the Crown, with a Prince whom he owns to be his Lawful Son and Heir; ſo young that he may live according to an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different Computation theſe 40 Years or more, and tho' they may ſeem quiet and dormant for a time, yet 'tis hardly to be expected they will let ſlip any opportunity, they may think favourable to the regaining their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Rights; 'tis to be conſider'd alſo, that they are of a Religion which no Oaths can bind or ſecure, when their Church will be a gainer by the Breach of them; add to this, that this Nation has been always the bar and hindrance to all the ambitious deſigns Projects of that Communion, and this has created an incurable hatred in them towards us, which they never fail to let us know upon all occaſions; ſo that we have all the reaſon in the World to look about us, eſpecially, conſidering there are ſuch Multitudes againſt us, and ſo few to aſſiſt us; tis true we have juſt made a Peace, after a charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and Expenſive War; but as 'twas the <hi>Number and Valour of our Troops</hi> that forc't it from an Ambitious and inveterate Enemy; ſo nothing but the <hi>ſame</hi> can preſerve it to us; for we are all pretty confident, that he whom we have had to deal with, has not been tender in break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the moſt ſolemn Leagues, when either his Intereſt or Ambition has thought it convenient.</p>
            <p>Beſides we ſee he has not deliver'd <hi>Briſack</hi> to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, which he ought to have done, but finds pretences to delay it till Spring, and we know not whether he'l do it then or no, unleſs he finds he ſhall be forc't to it. Add to theſe, the great Number of <hi>Jacobites</hi> we have at home,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101249:18"/>who are a People reſtleſs and uneaſie; ready to Plot and execute any baſe and Villainous deſigns: Add alſo, that the King of <hi>Spain</hi> lies a dying, and the King of <hi>France</hi> has <hi>great Armies</hi> ready to enter into that Country; at ſo favourable a Juncture, to ſupport the right he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to that Crown; I ſay, all theſe things truly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd, <hi>Here's a concurrence of Circumſtances that never happen'd at once till now, nor perhaps never may again, that call upon us, and oblige us to keep up our Standing Forces at this Time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I think I have ſaid enough to convince any reaſonable Perſons of the Neceſſity of an Army at this time; which is all need be done, to anſwer this <hi>Hiſtorian;</hi> for if there is a neceſſity of an Army, 'tis certain it ſhou'd be one that may be ſufficient and able to cope with any force our Enemies may bring againſt us; or elſe we had as good have none at all: In former times when our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours had but <hi>five</hi> or <hi>ten thouſand</hi> Men in Arms there was no occaſion for our having a greater Number; but if they encreaſe to a Hundred thouſand or more, we muſt alſo be in ſome tolerable degree equal with them, or be contented to be Inſulted or Invaded by thoſe that are ſtronger; this is ſo very plain and clear, I ſhall argue it no farther, but ſhew the danger of truſting to a <hi>Militia,</hi> when they are attack'd by regular and diſciplin'd Troops and ſo conclude,</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Want</hi> of a ſufficient Number of Standing and Diſciplin'd Troops may be learnt from the <hi>Dutch,</hi> who were almoſt brought to the brink of ruin, in the Year 1672, when the <hi>French,</hi> who ſeldom fail to make their advantages of the over-ſites and Neglects of their Neighbours; Invaded them with mighty Armies, which
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101249:19"/>like a Torrent over-run Three large Provinces, taking above Forty ſtrong Towns in almoſt as many days. Whoever reads Sir <hi>William Temple</hi>'s Obſervations, will find that Great Man makes out the <hi>want of regular Standing Forces,</hi> one of the chief reaſons of their Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes, which had like to have been the utter Ruin of their Commonwealth; he ſays, <hi>it was their too great parſimony in disbanding the beſt of their Foreign Officers and Troops, after the Peace of</hi> Munſter; he tells us, <hi>thoſe Miniſters who had the Directions of Affairs, bent their Chief application to the Strength and Order of their Fleet, and totally Neglected their Land Army;</hi> ſo that thoſe few Souldiers they had were without Diſcipline. Theſe were the Reaſons made the <hi>French</hi> King ſuppoſe their Conqueſt Eaſie, and invited him to invade them, and upon Tryal he found he was not miſtaken, for they were not able to reſiſt him; tho' 'tis Obſervable that for Twenty Years before, they had been regulating their <hi>Militia,</hi> and endeavouring to make it ſerviceable, but 'twas ſo far from being ſo, that they ſuffer'd the <hi>French</hi> to become Maſters of their ſtrong <hi>Fortified Towns</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt as ſoon as they approach'd them, this is ſo lively and near an Example and ſo well fitted for our Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that methinks we ſhou'd take warning by it, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out deſiring to make the Experiment our ſelves.</p>
            <q>Foelix quem faciunt aliena pericula Cautum.</q>
            <p>How often has <hi>Poland,</hi> (a Country theſe Gentlemen are pleas'd to produce as an Inſtance of ſupporting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by a <hi>Militia</hi>) been revag'd and Inſulted by the <hi>Sweeds, Muſcovites,</hi> and <hi>Tartars,</hi> and ſuffer'd all the Extremities of Fire and Sword <hi>for the want of Standing and Regular Troops.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:101249:19"/>
            <p>Now I think I have ſufficiently ſhew'd the weakneſs of theſe Gentlemen's Arguments, and the <hi>abſolute Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity</hi> for our keeping up a <hi>Land Force,</hi> not by <hi>falſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations</hi> of things, but by a true conſideration of the preſent Circumſtances of Affairs, which is the only means to find the right of this Matter; So that I hope no true <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> who deſires the good of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, will be for the <hi>Disbanding the Forces</hi> till either our Neighbours have done the ſame, or that our <hi>Militia</hi> be ſo well regulated, that they may be able to Cope with any <hi>Diſciplin'd Troops</hi> whatſoever.</p>
            <p>For ſuppoſing, on our <hi>Immediate Disbanding our For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> any of our Neighbours ſhou'd think it the Critical time to attempt an Invaſion of <hi>England,</hi> before our <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia</hi> was ready to receive them, and this is none of the unlikelieſt Suppoſitions, wou'd ask theſe Gentlemen, if we ſhou'd not have ſome Reaſons for apprehending of of danger, when we have only the Succeſs of a Fleet to depend on, ſeveral Accidents might happen to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it unſerviceable to us, as our being kept in Port by contrary Winds, or our not being in a readineſs enough to hinder them, theſe are no very Improbable things, we have had the knowledge of their Poſſibility by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, and I ſay, imagining it happen'd that we were Invaded, I deſire to know what reſiſtance our <hi>Militia</hi> cou'd make againſt 20 <hi>or</hi> 30 <hi>Thouſand Regular Troops</hi> well Diſciplin'd and inur'd the War; we ſhou'd then <hi>wiſh</hi> for our <hi>Forces</hi> when they were not to be had, nay perhaps when a conſiderable Number of them were liſted in the Enemies Service, having been ſo ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully us'd here as to be turn'd looſe to Want and Miſery, after having ſpent their Youth and Blood in our Service; and what Nation wou'd pitty us? Wou'd not all the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101249:20"/>World cry out we deſervedly fell Martyrs of our Folly? that we cou'd blame none but our ſelves, for that our ſelves only were the Authors of our Deſtruction.</p>
            <p>After all that can be ſaid on both ſides, and to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe even all the Idle Chimeras theſe <hi>Grumbletonians</hi> wou'd fright us with, the whole matter abſolutely depends on our cooſing one of theſe two things, viz. <hi>either to truſt King</hi> William <hi>or King</hi> Lewis.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
